Alan Hans Bitterlich Koning

Electronic Engineer, Data Scientist, MBA, M.A.

56961924893

☑ Alan.bitterlich.k@gmail.com

Los adobes 1650, Lo Barnechea, Santiago.

SUMMARY

Electronic Civil Engineer from Universidad Técnica Federico Santa María, Master in Business Administration (MBA) and Master in Sales and International Business (M.A) in Germany. Diploma in big data and decision making (PUC). Specialist in technology and data science, 4 years of experience. User of programming languages and software's. Experience in automation projects, controllers, software, industry, shipping, real estate, business administration, organization, contract management, investments, advertising, marketing, start-ups, among others.

EXPERIENCE

Data Scientist

Agrosuper



10/2022 - currently

Rancagua

Data Scientist Software leader

Inversiones e inmobiliaria Futura S.A

8/2021 - 5/2022

Viña del mar

CEO

Data Scientist

Inversiones e inmobiliaria Keule S.A.

11 01/2019 - 12/2021

Puerto Montt

Project Department Manager **Electronic Engineer**

Bitter ingeniería Spa

1 01/2016 - 12/2018

Puerto Montt

PERSONAL INFORMATION

RUT: 17.513.364-k Class B license Advanced English (C1 Toefl) Basic German Github: Alan-Hans/Portafolio-DataScientist

EDUCATION

Diplomado in Big Data for Decision Making (2022) University Católica de Chile

Santiago, Chile

Master of arts in International Marketing and Sales (2021) **University of Applied Sciences FH**

Münster, Germany

MBA in Business Administration (2021) **University Austral de Chile** Valdivia, Chile

Electronic Civil Engineering (2015), Exchange program **KTH Royal Institute of Technology**

Stockholm, Sweden

Electronic Civil Engineering (2010-2016)

University técnica Federico Santa María

Valparaíso, Chile

Secundary and Primary school Windsord School

Valdivia, Chile

DETAILED EXPERIENCE

Data Scientist (10/2022 - currently) Agrosuper

Data scientist in administration and financial management. In the field of operational excellence. Management and leading projects about data and big data, empowering the value of the organization.

Projects developed: predict operational results, anomalies detections, raw material forecasting and others.

Key terms: Azure, data bricks, gcp, python, R, Sql, teams, Agile, neural networks, featuring enginer, predictive models, prescriptive models, clustering, providers, anomalies detections, operational results, forecasting.

Data Scientist and software leader (08/2021 - 5/2022) Futura S.A

Tasks performed: developed predictive models, pricing models, forecasting models, prepare ETL, using gcp and aws. Different ides of python development. Prepare data and presentations using tableu.

Software used: Python, Jupiter notebook, tableau, PostgreSQL.

Software development for apartment buildings. Hardware and software involved. People registration, sensors, actuators, cloud communication and Raspberry py. In charge of Scrum master team and project general manager.

Software involved in the project: PYTHON, PHP, HTML5, CSS3, JavaScript, Bootstrap / Material Design. Cloud: AWS. Methodology: Agile.

Data Scientist (01/2019 - 12/2021) Inversiones e Inmobiliaria Keule S.A

In charge of the fish counter department, main functions:

Contract manager, organizer of team and telework team, monitor vessels operating in Norway with accuracy. The work was performed in english language with Norwegian colleagues on a daily basis and continuously over time.

Information analysis: analyze information regarding fish in order to perform calibrations, reduce equipment error and increase productivity. This was done through the use of data and big data, using trend information, error, average, machine learning. Software used: Excel, Python and software for calibration.

Report generation: reports with sensitive information for management and customers. Example of content: product mortality, trend graphs, parameters, instrumentation error, cross-checking information. This was performed between different ship systems.

Calibration: Implementation of adjustments to instrumentation on board and online.

Software used: Python, Jupiter notebook, tableau, SQL.

CEO (01/2019 - 12/2021) Inversiones e Inmobiliaria Keule S.A

Tasks performed: Direct interaction with clients and suppliers, project management, company management and team of the company (company personnel). Search and quotation of projects, general administration (project control), company marketing, among others.

Projects carried out:

- -In charge of WingTech fish counting system, direct communication with foreign partner company. (Norway).
- -Scrum master and product owner from a development. This development consists in an interface and ship monitoring, using IOT system, some of the languages used: PHP, HTML5, CSS3, JavaScript, Bootstrap / Material Design. MySQL and MongoDB, HighCharts Graphics, Cloud: AWS. Methodology: Agile.

Project Department Manager (01/2017 - 12/2018) Bitter Ingeniería SPA

Tasks performed: Direct interaction with clients and suppliers, project and team management (company personnel), search and quotation of projects, general administration (project control), company marketing, among others.

Projects carried out:

- -Charge: site manager. Electrical assembly of Lousiana Pacific plant. Plant expansion, project amount 700,000,000 CLP\$.
- -Position: construction manager. Electrical assembly of Ayacara fish farm. Plant expansion project, amount 250,000,000 CLP\$.

Electronic Engineer (09/2016 - 01/2017) Bitter Ingeniería SPA

Tasks performed: Integration of maritime systems, work on wheel boats, specifically on the salmon loading and unloading system. Worked using SQL database and WINCC for the SQL database and WINCC, for the registration system. WINCC and Step 7 for the programming of the actions.

Internship and tesis (03/2015 - 09/2015) AC3E. (Valparaiso, Chile)

Internship (04/2014 - 07/2014) Telefónica del sur. (Valdivia, Chile)

Electrician (12/2013 - 02/2014) Bitter y vic. (Valdivia, Chile)

Projects and Portfolio (Proof of work, on development)

- -Data scientist projects and general: https://github.com/Alan-Hans/Portafolio-DataScientist
- -SQL exercise: https://github.com/Alan-Hans/Portafolio-

DataScientist/blob/main/SQL exersice.ipynb

-Tutorial of AWS, ETL procedures: https://github.com/Alan-Hans/Portafolio-

DataScientist/blob/main/Tutorial ETL AWS.ipynb

COURSES AND ADVANCED TRAINING

- Seminar Ser-Cap, Solar energy On-grid, 2017.
- Platzi courses, https://platzi.com/p/alanhans/ related to data Scientist, data engineering and technologies.

COMPUTING AND SOFTWARE

- Microsoft Office (Word, Excel, Powerpoint) advanced.
- SAP.
- Windows, Linux y Mac Os.
- ❖ AutoCAD.
- Blockchain user

SOFTWARE

- ❖ Python, Jupiter Notebook, librarys and IDE's of development.
- ❖ Javascript, HTML, CSS.
- PostgreSQL, SQL, bases de datos.
- ❖ Power BI.
- Data studio.
- ❖ Tableau.
- . GITHUB.
- Agile Methodologies.
- OKrs
- ❖ AWS, GCP, AZURE.
- Neural networks.

SKILLS AND INTERESTS

I am a young, optimistic, sporty and responsible professional, who wishes to develop my knowledge as an engineer, project manager, blockchain, big data, data analysis, data scientist and decision-making consultant.

In addition, I develop myself in entrepreneurship and startups of technological type, with the experience of creation and management of 3 companies.

I maintain good interpersonal relationships and have management and leadership skills, at different levels and environments.